Thomas Szasz Papers
Thomas Szasz Papers
- Writings by Szasz
  - Miscellany
    - M. B. Eddy, 10 Jun 1974; draft with revisions, 16pp. (Box 349)
    - [on malingering] (Box 349)
    - The medicalization of sex, 1991; possibly a letter to the editor; typescript, 2pp. (Box 349)
    - Medicine and madness, in Encyclopedia Britannica Yearbook, 1974; reprints (Box 349)
    - Memorandum on proposed reforms in mental health legislation, prepared for Senator Robert F. Kennedy, photocopy of revised draft, 15pp. (Box 349)
    - The mental health ethic, clean typescript, 39pp. (Box 349)
    - [on mental illness as a legal defense], draft with revisions, 20 pp.; typescript carbon, 14 pp. (Box 349)
    - Mental illness a myth, in The ABC of Psychology, 1982; photocopy of published article (Box 349)
    - [on the mind], draft with revisions, 8pp.; Chapter 1 of unidentified book (Box 349)
    - The "morality" of drug controls, drafts, some with revisions (Box 349)
    - The myth of mental illness, drafts with revisions (Box 349)
    - Myth of mental illness, in Encyclopedia of Mental Health, 1998; galleys (Box 349)
    - Myth of mental illness, in Encyclopedia of Psychology, 1984; galleys (Box 349)
    - Myth of psychotherapy, in What is Psychotherapy? Contemporary Perspectives, 1988-1990; includes correspondence with Milton H. Erickson Foundation (Box 349)
    - National Review, possibly a letter to the editor; draft with revisions, clean carbon (Box 349)
    - Negro slavery and institutional slavery, chapter 4 of unidentified book (Box 349)
    - Nijinsky, 1982; numerous drafts with revisions; 2 folders (Box 349)
    - Open letter to Blue Cross/Blue Shield, 1978; includes issue of "Psychiatric News" with related article (Box 349)
    - The politics of psychotherapy, several drafts, revised; the abbreviation "PSA" is used on several pages (Box 349)
    - [on poor quality of care in public hospitals], drafts with revisions (Box 350)
    - Prohibitions and their problems table, several drafts of chart ("Table X"), some with revisions (Box 350)
    - Proposed resolution of the National Ex-Patient Teleconference: The rights of mental patients a/k/a Psychiatric slavery, Jul 1989; clean typescript, 3pp. (Box 350)
    - [on psychiatric atrocities], possibly a letter to the editor; draft with revisions, 7pp. (Box 350)
    - Psychiatry, written in the form of a dialog, on whether or not one of the speakers is insane (Box 350)
    - [on psychiatry and the law], draft, heavily revised, 16pp. (Box 350)
    - [on psychological testing and diagnosis], chapter or conference paper; draft, heavily revised, about 45pp. (Box 350)
    - Psychomanagerial despotism, drafts with revisions (Box 350)
    - [on racism as mental illness], clean typescript, 2pp. (Box 350)
    - [on religious liberty], from conference or symposium; typescript with a few revisions, 4pp. (Box 350)
    - [on religious liberty and drug use], typescript with a few revisions, 3pp. (Box 350)
    - [on the rights of mental patients], rough drafts, heavily revised (Box 350)
    - [on sex education], drafts, annotated with the phrase "Family Weekly"; probably a letter to the editor (Box 350)
    - The State as therapist, Chapter 21 of unidentified book; one set of pages is stamped as pp. 596-621 (Box 350)
    - The State, a mighty Gibraltar, drafts, clean, some also titled "Chapter 1" (Box 350)
    - Statement on Scientology, for the Church of Scientology in Germany; drafts with revisions, about 16pp. each (Box 350)
    - Storing people, chart listing all the ways human beings may be confined; draft with revisions, 1p. (Box 350)
    - The Syntax of suffering, drafts, some with revisions (Box 350)
    - [Tables of contents], TOCs for various books, with the names/dates of periodicals wherein the various pieces were published (Box 350)
    - The Treason of the doctors I: The violation of the right to one's body, drafts, revised; some are labeled "Chapter 2"; 2 folders (Box 350)
    - The Treason of the doctors II: The violation of the right to one's personality, drafts, revised; some are labeled "Chapter 3"; 2 folders (Box 350)
    - The War on drugs is lost [contributor], 12 Feb 1996; one point of view, contributed to larger article published in National Review (Box 350)
    - What is psychoanalytic treatment?, outline and 3-page summary (Box 351)
    - [Whole Earth Catalog contribution], 1988 (Box 351)
    - Words have consequences, medical language/terminology; draft with revisions, 11pp. (Box 351)
    - [ZWANG blurb], 2003; quote from Szasz praising the launch of the magazine, published by the International Association Against Psychiatric Assault (Box 351)
    - End notes, unidentified, includes a few pages of references (Box 351)
    - Epilogues, unidentified, 2 folders (Box 351)
    - Sections, unidentified, 3 folders (Box 351)
    - Fragments, unidentified, 5 folders (Box 351)
    - Fragments, unidentified, 11 folders (Box 352)
    - Miscellaneous notes, handwritten (Box 352)
- Writings by others
  This series includes drafts, typescripts, advance reading copies, etc. of articles, essays, papers, books, book chapters, and so on. There are also three folders of humorous skits written and performed by SUNY Upstate psychiatry students in residency. Some have annotations, revisions, comments, or edits by Szasz. If the item was eventually published, publication date is given in parentheses following the title.
  - Addams, Marti / Sex and Schrodinger's cat, typescript of novel; 3 folders (Box 353)
  - Alexander, George J. / Trial by champion, 1971; incomplete (footnotes and concluding section of paper only); includes letter from author; Alexander published an article with this title in 1984 but it is quite different from this (Box 353)
  - Alinsky, Ann / The suicide, includes prefatory note by Szasz stating that he received the manuscript in the mail (Box 353)
  - American News Service / untitled article, drafts of article with Szasz's revisions (Box 353)
  - Arkes, Hadley / The philosopher in the city (1981), pp. 1-223, bound photocopy of proofs or advance reading copy, with annotations, underlining etc (Box 353)
  - Arkes, Hadley / The philosopher in the city (1981), pp. 224-455, bound photocopy of proofs or advance reading copy, with annotations, underlining etc (Box 354)
  - Balistreri, Maggie / The evasion-English dictionary (2003), two typescripts, slightly different; includes letter from author requesting blurb (Box 354)
  - Balyk, Edward D. / Freud's fibs, fantasies, and fallacies, 50-page excerpt; includes letter from author (Box 354)
  - Bayles, Michael / Morality and population policy (1980), unbound signatures; note taped to front says "Susan Marie Szasz"; 2 folders (Box 354)
  - Bohart, Arthur and Tallman, Karen / How clients make therapy work (1999), proofs; includes letter from publisher requesting Szasz's opinion; 4 folders (Box 354)
  - Bonac, Vesna A. / Communicative psychoanalysis with children (2000), typescript, pp. 1-50, with handwritten note from author on first page (Box 354)
  - Bonac, Vesna A. / Communicative psychoanalysis with children (2000), typescript, pp. 51-169, with handwritten note from author on first page; 2 folders (Box 355)
  - Caplan, Bryan / The economics of Szasz (2006), blind peer-review copy; 2 copies (Box 355)
  - Childs, Roy A. / Liberty against power (1994), collection of Childs' essays, edited by Joan Kennedy Taylor; typescript, clean, pp-1-80; 6 folders (Box 355)
  - Cioffi, Frank / Freud and the question of pseudoscience, proofs; 2 folders (Box 355)
  - Cohen-Cole, Linn / Double bind (2007), bound manuscript; includes letter from author (Box 356)
  - Colgan, Michael / Your personal vitamin profile (1982), photocopy of revised galleys; 3 folders (Box 376)
  - Curtis, A.B. / Depression is a choice, advance uncorrected proof; includes publisher's prospectus (Box 356)
  - Daly, Robert W. / Before depression: The medieval vice of acedia (2007), typescript; author was colleague of Szasz at SUNY Upstate (Box 356)
  - Danylak, Joan Kikel / Honoring poets and professional and creative people (2003), signed and inscribed to Szasz; self-published (Box 356)
  - Eisenach, Eldon J. / Two worlds of liberalism: Religion and politics in Hobbes, Locke, and Mill (1981), photocopied proofs, annotated; pencilled note on first page says "Susan Marie Szasz"; 3 folders (Box 356)
  - Elshtain, Jean Bethke / The family in political thought (1982), galleys, marked; pencilled note on first page says "Susan Szasz/JS" (Box 376)
  - Elshtain, Jean Bethke / Public man, private woman (1981), photocopied proofs, annotated; pencilled note on first page says "Susan Szasz"; 2 folders (Box 356)
  - Evans, Rod, and Verykoukis, Nico / America's rejection of freedom and responsibility, typescript; 3 folders (Box 357)
  - Exline, John D. / A critical analysis of the views of Thomas Szasz, 1980; college paper, typescript (Box 357)
  - Farber, Seth / Unholy madness: The church's surrender to psychiatry (1999), proofs; 2 folders (Box 357)
  - Fisher, Gary / Rethinking our war on drugs (2006), typescript; 4 folders (Box 357)
  - Foucault, Michel (ed.) / I, Pierre Riviere, having slaughtered my mother, my sister, and my brother (1976), uncorrected first proof, with annotations (Box 357)
  - Frank, Leonard (ed.) / The history of shock treatment (1975), photocopy of proofs or possibly pasted-up pages; 2 folders (Box 357)
  - Frank, Leonard (ed.) / The Szasz quotationary (2011), typescript; 3 folders (Box 358)
  - Freeman, Lucy and Hoffman, Lisa / The ordeal of Stephen Dennison (1970), photocopy of revised typescript, with additional revisions; 3 folders (Box 358)
  - Friedberg, John / An introduction to the ideas of Thomas Szasz, photocopy of corrected typescript (Box 358)
  - Fuller, Robert C. / Stairways to heaven: Drugs in American religious history (2000), typescript; 2 folders (Box 358)
  - Galston, William A. / Justice and the human good (1980), photocopied proofs, annotated; pencilled note on first page says "Susan Marie Szasz"; 2 folders (Box 358)
  - Gardner, James M. / The disposable people, photocopied pages; includes letter from the authors requesting Szasz's comments (Box 358)
  - Gardner, James M. / The disposable people, photocopied pages (Box 359)
  - Glasser, William / Reality therapy in action (2000), 1999; bound typescript; includes letter from publisher (Box 359)
  - Hammerschlag, Carl / The dancing healers, bound typescript (Box 359)
  - Hamowy, Ronald / Canadian medicine: A study in restricted entry (1984), photocopied proofs or galleys; 3 folders (Box 376)
  - Hans, James S. / The play of the world, galleys with revisions in red ink; pencilled note on first page reads "Susan Marie Szasz" (Box 377)
  - Harrison, Steven / Being one: Finding our self in relationship (1999), 1998; first proofs; 2 folders (Box 359)
  - Harrison, Steven / Doing nothing: Meditation, thought, and reality (1997, as "Doing Nothing: Coming to the End of the Spiritual Search"), bound typescript (Box 359)
  - Hebald, Carol / The heart too long suppressed [copy 1], 1997; typescript of memoir; includes letter from author; 4 folders (Box 359)
  - Hebald, Carol / The heart too long suppressed [copy 2], 1997; typescript of memoir; includes letter from author; 4 folders (Box 360)
  - Hillman, James and Boer, Charles (ed.s) / Freud's own cookbook, includes jacket and publisher's prospectus; 3 folders (Box 360)
  - Hocutt, Max / Szasz on mental illness, typescript of paper; includes letter from author (Box 360)
  - Horrobin, D.F. / Schizophrenia: The illness that made us human (1998), proofs for publication in Medical Hypotheses (Box 360)
  - Jennings, David / The confusion between disease and illness in clinical medicine, 1986; "FINAL COPY" photocopy of typescript (Box 360)
  - Johnston, Jill / Paper daughter (1985), advance uncorrected proof; 2 copies (Box 360)
  - Kiester, Edwin / The religion of psychiatry and its antichrist, typescript copies, with Szasz's edits (Box 360)
  - Klein, Thelma / Savage scruple: A woman's life (1997), advance galleys; includes letter from publisher requesting Szasz's comments (Box 360)
  - Krulla, J.H. / Illegal drugs, 2006; novel excerpt; includes letter from author requesting assistance (Box 361)
  - Leifer, Ron / The happiness project (1997), 1994; disbound typescript; 3 folders (Box 361)
  - Loria, Donald / Psychiatry and sacrilege: Szasz speaks to silence, photocopy of typescript (Box 361)
  - Mann, David / A simple theory of the self (1994), proofs, with annotations; 2 folders (Box 361)
  - Masson, Jeffrey Moussaieff / Final analysis: The making and unmaking of a psychoanalyst (1990), bound un-copyedited manuscript, with annotations (Box 361)
  - Mastellone, Neil / Cosmic storm, novel typescript; 4 folders (Box 361)
  - McBroom, Patricia / untitled story, 1984; photocopy of typescript with Szasz's revisions; includes correspondence between Szasz and author (Box 361)
  - McWhinney, Ian Renwick / Are we on the brink of a major transformation of clinical method?, "DRAFT ONLY" photocopy of typescript, with comments by Szasz (Box 361)
  - Nessel, Jerry Thomas / Thomas S. Szasz M.D.: Descripcion y analysis, 1975; medical college dissertation; bound typescript carbon, in Spanish (Box 377)
  - Niemeyer, Robert A. and Raskin, Jonathan D. / (De)Constructing disorder (2000), 1999; first proofs; eventually published as "Constructions of Disorder: Meaning-Making Frameworks for Psychotherapy"; 4 folders (Box 362)
  - O'Meara, Kelly Patricia / Psyched out (2006), bound typescript, pp. 1-160; 3 folders (Box 362)
  - Paley, Michael R. / Orthodox Judaism, liberalism, and libertarianism: When secularism becomes a religion (2006), typescript; 2 folders (Box 362)
  - Parrish, Richard Henry / Defining drugs: How government became the arbiter of pharmaceutical fact (2003), 2000-2003; bound proofs of book; 3 folders (Box 362)
  - Parrish, Richard Henry / Defining drugs: How government became the arbiter of pharmaceutical fact (2003), 2000-2003; copy of PhD dissertation on which book is based, pp. 1-160; 2 folders (Box 362)
  - Parrish, Richard Henry / Defining drugs: How government became the arbiter of pharmaceutical fact (2003), 2000-2003; copy of PhD dissertation on which book is based, pp. 161-230 (Box 363)
  - Pelikan, Herbert Rainer / Der begriff "Geisteskrankheit" bei Viktor E. Frankl und by Thomas Szasz, 1986; thesis or dissertation?; includes very friendly letter from author (Box 363)
  - Piko, Bettina / Socio-cultural stress in modern societies and the myth of anxiety in Eastern Europe, 2002; proofs, signed and inscribed to Szasz (Box 363)
  - Platkin, Charles / Breaking the pattern (2002), 2001; bound manuscript; includes letter from author (Box 363)
  - Rae, Douglas / Equalities (1981), photocopied proofs, annotated; pencilled note on first page says "Susan Marie Szasz"; 2 folders (Box 363)
  - Residents / skit, "From rags to rayon", Dec 1962; humorous skits/song parodies featuring spoofs of Szasz (Box 363)
  - Residents / skit, "Problems in living through Thursdays", undated; humorous skits/song parodies featuring spoofs of Szasz (Box 363)
  - Residents / skits, Dec 1977; humorous skits/song parodies featuring spoofs of Szasz (Box 363)
  - Review of Existential Psychology and Psychiatry / Vol XXIII special issue, 1997; photocopied proofs of special issue entirely focused on Szasz; includes one article by him; 4 folders (Box 363)
  - Ross, Colin and Pam, Alvin / Pseudoscience in biological psychiatry: Blaming the body (1995), typescript, pp. 1-80, with notes/edits on first few pages (Box 363)
  - Ross, Colin and Pam, Alvin / Pseudoscience in biological psychiatry: Blaming the body (1995), typescript, pp. 81-368, with notes/edits on first few pages; 4 folders (Box 364)
  - Schulte, Gunter / Ein auszug aus meinem leben, 1983; includes letter from author (Box 364)
  - Seidel, Jason A. / Empirical evidence disconfirms the biopsychiatric ontology of mental disorders, 1998; doctoral dissertation (Box 364)
  - Shapiro, Michael J. / Language and political understanding: The politics of discursive practices (1981), photocopied proofs, annotated; pencilled note on first page says "Susan Marie Szasz"; 3 folders (Box 364)
  - Sharma, Sohan Lal / Psychotherapy and social forces: The dialectics of psychotherapy (1986, as "The therapeutic dialogue"), 1984; photocopy of revised typescript, TOC through ch. 3, with foreword by Szasz; includes letter from author to Szasz; 2 folders (Box 364)
  - Sharma, Sohan Lal / Psychotherapy and social forces: The dialectics of psychotherapy (1986, as "The therapeutic dialogue"), 1984; photocopy of revised typescript, ch. 4-12, with foreword by Szasz; 6 folders (Box 365)
  - Sharma, Sohan Lal / Psychotherapy and social forces: The dialectics of psychotherapy (1986, as "The therapeutic dialogue"), bound typescript (Box 377)
  - Skrabanek, Petr / The death of humane medicine, bound typescript, annotated; 2 folders (Box 365)
  - Slovenko, Ralph / Psychiatry and criminal culpability (1995), typescript, pp. 1-306, page numbers adjusted but no other markings; 2 folders (Box 365)
  - Slovenko, Ralph / Psychiatry and criminal culpability (1995), typescript, pp. 307-711, page numbers adjusted but no other markings; 3 folders (Box 366)
  - Society for Individual Freedom / Liberty against psychiatry, 1983; photocopy of revised typescript, pp. 1-240; includes letter from Society to Szasz; 5 folders (Box 366)
  - Spillane, Robert / Gardner on leadership (2005), bound white paper, eventually published as book chapter (Box 366)
  - Stedman / [unidentified dictionary], probably Stedman's Psychiatry Words, part of the "Stedman's Word Books" series; photocopies of heavily-revised pages; 2 folders (Box 366)
  - Strasser, Alison and Freddie / Existential Time-Limited Therapy: The Wheel of Existence (1997), typescript, pp. 1-80, with notes/edits on first few pages (Box 366)
  - Strasser, Alison and Freddie / Existential Time-Limited Therapy: The Wheel of Existence (1997), typescript, pp. 81-end, with notes/edits on first few pages; 2 folders (Box 367)
  - Sullum, Jacob / Saying yes: In defense of drug use (2003), bound typescript; includes letter from author requesting blurb (Box 367)
  - Swartz, Ronald / Five essays on educational problems, bound typescript (Box 367)
  - Swartz, Ronald / Summerhill revisited: Searching for a perspective on the life and work of A.S. Neill (1986), review of two books about Neill; typescript; includes letter from editor (Box 367)
  - Szasz, Suzanne / Suzanne Szasz: A retrospective (1982), Hungarian National Gallery exhibit catalogue on the work of photographer Suzanne Szasz (born Zsuzsanna Szekely), relationship to Thomas Szasz unknown (Box 367)
  - Szasz, Suzy / Living with it (1990), autobiography/memoir by Szasz's daughter
    - First? Draft, handwritten, in sections by date, covering childhood through the end of 1983; 5 folders (Box 367)
    - First? Draft, cont., handwritten, in sections by date, covering childhood through the end of 1983; 7 folders (Box 368)
    - Early draft, pp. 1-300, typescript, heavily revised; 3 folders (Box 368)
    - Early draft, pp. 301-823, typescript, heavily revised; 6 folders (Box 369)
    - "3d draft", typescript, heavily revised, many pages physically cut and pasted; 5 folders (Box 369)
    - Draft [A], 5 folders (Box 370)
    - Draft [B], pp. 371-725, incomplete; 5 folders (Box 370)
    - Draft [C], pp. 1-179, typescript, unmarked; 2 folders (Box 370)
    - Draft [C], pp. 180-373, typescript, unmarked; 2 folders (Box 371)
    - Draft [D], pp. 1-179, typescript, same as Draft C, but heavily edited/revised; 5 folders (Box 371)
    - Draft [E], pp. 1-320, typescript, with edits/revisions; 4 folders (Box 371)
    - Draft [E], pp. 321-381, typescript, with edits/revisions (Box 372)
    - Draft [F], typescript, same as Draft E, with similar edits but in different hand; 5 folders (Box 372)
    - "Next to last draft", pp. 1-459, typescript, revised; 5 folders (Box 372)
    - "Next to last draft", pp. 460-523, typescript, revised (Box 373)
    - Epilogue drafts (Box 373)
    - Proofs, 3 folders (Box 373)
  - Tummey, Robert and Turner, Tim / Critical issues in mental health, typescript; includes letter from authors requesting Szasz write the Foreword (Box 373)
  - van Eijk-Osterholt, C.A. / That will teach them, 1973; typescript carbons of excerpts from book; includes correspondence between Szasz and authors (Box 373)
  - Vatz, Richard E. and Weinberg, Lee S. / The rhetorical paradigm in psychiatric history: Thomas Szasz and the myth of mental illness (1993), typescript of book chapter, published in "Discovering the history of psychiatry" (Box 373)
  - Vice, Janet Arline / From patients to persons: Psychiatric critiques of Thomas Szasz, Peter Sedgwick, and R.D. Laing, doctoral dissertation; 2 folders (Box 373)
  - Vida, Judith E. / Living art: Assaulting the myths of art and illness, 2002; signed and inscribed to Szasz (Box 373)
  - Wain, Martin / Freud's answer (1998), advance uncorrected proof (Box 374)
  - Wasserstrom, William / Phoenix on Turtle Island: D.H. Lawrence in Henry Adams' America (1978), published item, from The Georgia Review, signed and inscribed to Szasz (Box 374)
  - Willensky, Ann / The myth of Thomas Szasz: A psychiatrist's crusade against psychiatry, 2002; typescript (Box 374)
  - Windholz, George / Psychiatric commitments of religious dissenters in Tsarist and Soviet Russia (1985), 1991; typescript of paper; includes letter from author and photocopy of published version (Box 374)
  - Winn, Marie / Children without childhood (1983), bound uncorrected page proofs, annotated (Box 374)
  - Wyatt, Ronald / Psychiatrists' and psychologists' positions on the psychosocial and medical models: An empirical approach, 1989; doctoral dissertation, bound, signed and inscribed to Szasz on title page (Box 374)
  - Wynne, Louis / Healing the hurting soul (2006), typescript; unclear whether this is an outline or the entire book (Box 374)
  - Yankelovich, Daniel and Barrett, William / Ego and instinct: Psychoanalysis and the science of man, 1968; photocopied typescript (Box 374)
  - Unidentified / Chapter 1: A passion for freedom, typescript of chapter from unidentified book about Szasz, with pencil revisions (Box 374)
  - Unidentified / Chapter 2: Dream interpretation and the interpretation of dreaming, typescript carbon (Box 374)
  - Unidentified / Chapter 2: The role of the couch in the psychoanalytic situation, typescript carbon (Box 374)
  - Unidentified / Untitled book on homosexuality, typescript, bound in four parts; 4 folders (Box 375)